Guide to the Amelia Stinson-Wesley papers, 1924-2004 RL.11711
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Amelia Stinson-Wesley papers
1924-2004
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Stinson-Wesley, Amelia
RL.11711
3 Linear Feet
Amelia Stinson-Wesley is an ordained Methodist minister and advocate for pastoral care of women and abuse survivors in North Carolina. Her papers consist of correspondence, academic writing, periodical excerpts, pamphlets, flyers, and handouts.
Conditions Governing Access
Folders 23 and 24 in Box 2 are restricted until 25 years after the creator's death.
Provenance
The Amelia Stinson-Wesley papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2018.
Biographical / Historical
Amelia Stinson-Wesley is an ordained Methodist minister and advocate for women's rights. She attended Meredith College in Raleigh for her undergraduate education from 1986-1990 and Duke Divinity School for her Masters of Divinity from 1990-1993. Stinson-Wesley served as the director of Response, part of the Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South, and has in other roles advocated for women and victims of physical/sexual abuse.
Collection Overview
Amelia Stinson-Wesley is an ordained Methodist minister and advocate for pastoral care of women and abuse survivors. Her papers consist of correspondence, academic writing, periodical excerpts, pamphlets, flyers, and handouts.
Methodist women -- United States -- North Carolina; Victims of family violence -- Pastoral counseling of; Women in the Methodist Church; Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture
- Women's Health and Violence Against Women, 1979-2004
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains materials related to Stinson-Wesley's work related to women's health advocacy and violence against women. It contains research and resources related to those topics.
  - Additional Worship Materials, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Breastfeeding, 2002 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Clergy Misconduct - Sexual Abuse Resources, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clergy Misconduct - Sexual Abuse Statistics and Articles, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Crime Prevention and Safety Guide, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Denominational Resources on Violence Against Women, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Direct Service Providers, 1995-2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Domestic Violence - Child Abuse Resources, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 10-12)
  - Domestic Violence - Elder Abuse Resources, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 13-16)
  - Domestic Violence - Spouse Abuse Resources, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 17-19)
  - Fellowship of Reconciliation Stop the Violence Campaign, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Handouts - Spirituality/Theology and Survivors, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Harassment General Information, 1990-1993 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Harassment Resources, 1991-1994 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Ministry of Healing (Connie Winter-Eulberg), 1994 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - New Mother Resources, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Pregnancy/Childbirth, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Pornography General Information, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Pornography Resources, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Prostitution Resources, 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 29-31)
  - Publicity on Response, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Rape Awareness Week Rape (Duke), 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Rape/Sexual Assault Information, 1984-1993 (Box 1, Folder 34-36)
  - Religious Press and Violence/Abuse, 1993-1996 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Religious Resources, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 38-39)
  - Response, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 40-42)
  - Ritual/Cult Abuse Resources, 1993-1994 (Box 1, Folder 43-44)
  - SASS Assistant Job, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Sexual Assault - (Campus), 1987-1991 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Sexual Assault - Resources, 1987-1992 (Box 1, Folder 47)
    Includes issues of Standing Together: A Publication of Rape Crisis of Durham
  - Sexual Assault Support Services - Safe Haven, 1991-1992 (Box 1, Folder 48-49)
  - Sexual Assault - Workshops, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Training Guide, 1995 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Victims of Violence/Violent Crime, 1981-1992 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Violence Against Women Handouts, 1979-1984 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Violence in the News, 1992-1996 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Worship Service Bulletin, circa 1991 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Worship Services/Healing Rituals Surviving Violence, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 56)
- Ministry Files, 1924-1998
  This series documents Amelia Stinson-Wesley's ministerial work, including pastoral care and advocacy. The materials consist of periodical clippings, personal writtings, flyers, handouts, and administrative records.
  - Abortion, 1992-1995 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - African-American Church, 1989-1994 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - AIDS (ministry to persons with), circa 1990 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Alcoholism, 1960-1991 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Anna Howard Shaw Center Boston School of Theology, 1991-1993 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Biblical Imagery of God as Female or Feminine, 1993 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Blessings (Handbook), 1992-1993 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Capital Punishment/Death Penalty, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - CEDAW, 1997-1998 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Correspondence w/Mary Jo for book (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Daughters of Tamar (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Duke Divinity School Women's Center 20th Anniversary Celebration, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Environment - Helpful Hints, 1991 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Environmental Concerns, 1989-1992 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Feminist Humor, 1990-1992 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Feminist Literature, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Feminist Literature/Bibliographies Religious, 1986-1991 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Film on Women Heads of State, 1994 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Fundamentalism (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Gender Roles/Stereotypes, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Hinduism, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - History of the Women's Movement, 1990's (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Homosexuality (UMC) (stances, information, etc.), 1992 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Humor, 1992 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Hunger, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Inclusive Language, 1977-1992 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Islam (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Liberation Theology, 1989-1990 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Lobbying Information, 1992-1994 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Men and Gender Issues, 1990-1991 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Menstruation, 1978-1992 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Methodist Federation for Social Action (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Methodist Herstory, 1975-1992 (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Methodist Herstory Anna Howard Shaw, 1967-1975 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Methodist Herstory Belle Harris Bennett, 1971-1981 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Methodist Herstory Frances Elizabeth Willard, 1967-1990 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Methodist Herstory Ordination, 1924-1956 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Methodist Herstory - Women in the Methodist Tradition (program), 1976-1993 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ministers, Women as (women in ministry, ordination of women), 1985-1991 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - National Organization for Women (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Nuclear War, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Open Hands/Reconciling Congregations Program, 1991-1992 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Peace/Non-Violence, 1990-1995 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Pleasant Garden UMC, 1967-1991 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Premenstrual Syndrome paper, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Racism, 1992 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Radical Stuff, 1989-1994 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Religious Sayings, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Resource Center for Women and Ministry in the South, 1991-1993 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Senior Thesis, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Speeches/Addresses, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Statistics, 1990-1992 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Through the Eyes of Women: Insights for Pastoral Care Fortress Press. spring 1996, 1993-1996 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - UM-related Women's Organizations, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - United Methodist Publishing House contract for youth materials, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Urban Ministry - Durham, 1969-1985 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Urban Ministry - Greensboro, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Women's Ordination, 1993-1994 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Personal Files, 1938-2001
  Conditions Governing Access
  Folders number 23 and 24 of Box 2 are restricted until 25 years after the creator's death.
  - Birth, 2000-2001 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    Restricted until 75 years after donor's death.
    Contains personal health information.
  - Infertility/Miscarriage, 1990-2001 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Meredith College, 1986-1989 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    Contains records from Amelia Stinson-Wesley's time in her undergraduate education.
  - Quilts/Afghans, 1938 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Recipes, 1991 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Resume, undated (Box 2, Folder 28)